thank you
hello and welcome it's March 28 2023
we're here in active bookstream number
1.012 off to you blue
great so we will be continuing our
discussion of the book governing
continuous transformation by Bhajan
kesri and this actually is going to wrap
up our coverage of this book we're not
going to go into the interviews covered
in the final section but we're going to
just cover this concluding part and then
wrap it up now and then in a few weeks
we will rejoin for a discussion section
or a discussion session so if you've
been following along with the live
streams to this point please get in
touch with us so that you can come on
and discuss some of the contents of the
book with us and hopefully the author is
available to join us
so we are the active inference Institute
of participatory online Institute that
is communicating learning and practicing
applied active inference you can reach
us at social media at all of these links
this is also a recorded and an archived
live stream so please provide us with
feedback so that we can improve on our
work all backgrounds and perspectives
are welcome here
we will be attempting to follow a good
video etiquette for live streams
um again there's many ways to
participate and collaborate with the
active Advanced Institute so if you are
interested in active inference and I'm
not yet collaborating with us just get
in touch active inference.org is our
website and there's a link to fill out a
form if you want to contribute in other
ways to The Institute besides joining us
on a live stream all right so the goal
of this bookstream is to conclude our
discussions of this book so we are going
to cover chapters
um
12 and 13. I would skip to the road back
so we're going to come to chapters 12
and 13 in this part three conclusion of
the book so chapter 12 is the future
research agenda and chapter 13 is
outperformance and survival as a matter
of self-organization so we can just
quickly introduce ourselves before
jumping into the contents I'm blue I'm
an independent research consultant in
New Mexico and I'll pass it off to Tyler
I'm Tyler I'm a protocol designer and
dab researcher also in California and
Daniel
I'm a researcher in California
did I say California foreign
I'm having visions of the beach okay so
chapter 12 has
um a few different sections again this
is like future research directions
discusses language and communication
embodied cognition artificial
intelligence board capabilities
developmental paths and then chapter 13
is really just a provocative conclusion
section
um and reminds us of some of the things
that we've learned in the book so far
and also about performance and survival
as a matter of like free energy
minimization so we will jump right into
the content uh Tyler do you want to read
this first um part of the abstract for
us sure
Effigy is the product of
multidisciplinary research project
connecting the dots among strategy
governance and Neuroscience research
opening a new conversation and headlines
introducing the free energy principles
strategy management FEG redefines the
Nexus structure and cognition ABV so
attention-based view advances the
dynamic capability View and from the
managerial to the core level that
establishes strategy as an inactive
Bayesian inference challenge
in terms of future research four areas
should Advance the optimization of FEG
one language and communication in
particular explainability purpose
prediction models and predictions to
body cognition in terms of a deeper
understanding around the neurobiology
underlying leadership's World engagement
as well as false inference
thanks and I'll do this next part
so the third area is artificial
intelligence in particular the strategy
application of AI powered machine
algorithms and fourth board capabilities
developmental paths in particular the
board's ability to collectively develop
meta capabilities free energy governance
as a framework provides the fundamental
building blocks that Empower a firm to
implement free energy minimization as a
self-organized principle structure
top-down bottom-up connectivity
cognition environmental enactment and
capabilities Duality management
within the fpg framework many vibrant
strategy research topics lend themselves
to be repurposed as a matter of
optimizing free energy minimization more
specifically survival rather than just
performance is the critical dependent
variable
so getting into sorry I'm trying to
navigate my board so getting into the
first section language and communication
um so I just pulled a couple of sentence
sentences out of this section
um Bijan says that the effectiveness of
free energy governance is critically
determined by transparency in
communication specifically around the
explainability of corporate purpose
prediction models and predictions to
obtain the most possible human energy
for productive effort
um and I think like this is really
something the communication overall is
an area that I would like to discuss
with Bijan further
um and but he does really kind of
clarify some of the questions that we've
been having over the last couple weeks
here in this section and even maybe the
next section about
um what specifically would like like
what specifically needs to be
communicated to all members of The Firm
um and at all levels so he really does
kind of clarify um he says if
organization is in emergent and
communication as we believe then it is
not a being but a becoming and that's a
quote from Taylor and Matt every 2000
and then he also says language is not a
tool but a force
um and with this I think he um
specifically is referring to like a
force that holds the firm together like
the um you know like contributes to the
self-organizing purpose and
sustainability of the firm
um and really he does uh talk a lot
about the purpose of the firm both in
this chapter and the next as like
everybody needs to know what is the
point for the firm's existence or for
the corporation's existence and so I
think that that is one aspect
um that might not necessarily be like a
governance strategy or
um
like something that's like internal like
a method of operation it's like you know
we think about like the top level
Executives but um something that like
why are we here what are we doing what
purpose are we serving as a corporation
as a company and I think that like that
is like one reasonable
um thing that can be communicated to
team members at all levels I don't know
if you guys have any thoughts here or
yeah so one thing that was like not
totally clear on about what Jean was
getting at here was what it means to
have explainable purpose because on one
level like the FEG like ultimate purpose
as I understand it is just like survival
I'm not sure if he meant purpose in like
some other sense of like
I don't know we are improving our
customers access to health care or
something like that that style level of
purpose and I wasn't quite clear what he
meant and he didn't quite get that many
examples so I'm not sure if you guys
have any thoughts or a clear sensible he
meant
yeah very good question it does seem to
be like there's uh
competing Communications around what
purpose is is purpose in this
deflationary sense merely survival and
persistence
at which point the clear communication
would just be around
whatever we are we need to continue even
if that involves change
versus more sub
purposes or topical performances which
that might resemble
standard non-survival oriented purposes
like to deliver the most X in y
yeah and it's I'm sorry
so I have a question also if survival is
the purpose of free energy governance or
if free energy minimization is the
purpose like I think about you know when
a firm swallows another firm like you
know in m a right like so you know but
then the little firm is not the purpose
is not to survive right like the purpose
is to become
um like I'm automated or or whatever
subsumed by the larger Corporation sorry
sorry if I got you offer interrupted
your thoughts
yeah and I well I guess something that I
feel like has been not
maybe I just haven't gotten it but not
necessarily consistently communicated as
like what their purpose is at the
highest level organization or at sub
levels so like in the same way as like a
pancreas cell may not know like the meta
purpose of like the pancreas I don't
know anything about biology so I'm not
mistaving something here
like does it is it necessarily true that
a individual team has to always keep in
mind the larger like meta purpose of
this organization or is it really okay
to have something that's more like
relevant to it's like subunit
organization
um and that hasn't always been clear to
me I'm still kind of struggling with
that
yeah I said I do think that like Jean
um specifically like when he was talking
about purpose and I think that it comes
more in the next chapter but it might
have been this chapter I don't know it's
all blurring together just one big
chapter but um he talks about like
purpose being at like on the front lines
right like the people that are on the
front lines like are as much determining
the purpose as they are communicating
the purpose so it might be not a
top-down directional communication
method like or like it's it's a
reciprocal like communicating the
purpose of the organization is probably
like a bi-directional information flow
ideally anyway so like people at the top
don't know what the people at the bottom
think the purpose is and the people at
the bottom don't know what people at the
top think the purpose is like there's no
unity and then the firm has a divided
purpose I guess
yeah I think that makes sense I mean my
my take on what he's saying is like it's
like this co-created maybe amorphous
thing that you're not necessarily like
pinning down and defining a thing on
like a landing page on your website
maybe something that's more of like a
shared felt and sense thing
um and so like that's what I think he's
saying but like
he doesn't explain it that way so I'm
not totally sure
yeah it's so these are good like
for sure
okay unless there's anything else we'll
go to embodied cognition
um where he says Brain body and
environment together form one integrated
cognitive embodied inactive extended
system
recasting the phenomena of false
inference and institutional psychosis as
a matter of impaired prediction error
minimization May highlight how
critically firm performance is also a
function of upper echelons embodied
cognition as determined amongst other by
psychological aspects as well as
neurobiology so like in this section
there was like a big like a whole bunch
of like neuro um
neuroscience
like about dopamine and the reward
system and predictionary minimization
and obviously like a firm doesn't have
like dopamine as a prediction error like
satisfier or like reward but like they
do like the whole firm is getting like a
dopamine hit but like the individual
members within that firm are getting
that dopamine um I guess when their
predictions are are correct
so um yeah this was kind of like a
it was like a big like stretch for me to
jump into like
um
I guess like the embodied cognition of
the firm is
the embodied cognition of
the upper echelon but shouldn't it be
like the embodied cognition of all of
the firm members or how do you get that
like bi-directional integration of
information without like
the bottom mattering just as much as the
top here I don't know this was like
fuzzy and weird for me
well so I mean I think like at one level
organization it's you know like all each
member's individual like dopamine
receptors and everything right but then
at the next level like you can abstract
that away and say maybe it's like the
response to uh financing like maybe
having more access to like Venture
Capital funding for example is a way of
like motivating action for an
organization or
um visitor growth on the landing page
it's just like the signal like hey like
you're going in the right direction like
double down here and keep keep moving or
keep exploring so that's maybe how I
would think of it at like an
organizational level
in a way that maybe feels kind of like
at a different level than just the sum
of the dopamine receptors of all of its
members
yeah like hearing you on the
gamification metrics for the
organization like hits on landing page
for a number of subscribers or the
number of viewers or the number of
Twitter followers
um all of those things that we know that
are like rewarding us personally with
the I mean like why I guess like that
that's like
um
like an easy bridge to cross regarding
like dopamine and institutional success
or prediction or minimization I think
well what I mean by that is a little bit
differently it's not like yeah like on
an individual level like if you see more
hits on your landing page like that's
gonna
have a dopamine response with you with
you as an individual but I think some of
these things like for example like press
coverage or giving Venture Capital
funding for example like those produce
systemic changes in an organization that
aren't just merely
about the dopamine response in the
individual and that's something that I
feel like is like a higher level change
that is like harder to explain
um and I'm struggling in terms of the
words from it but just like when you get
like a lot of funding into an
organization or a startup or you start
getting traction on something like it
produces a kind of like social contagion
I don't know if that's the right word
that
is more than just the sum of its parts
of dopamine changes
if it's individuals
cool
um anything else here or we can move on
to
artificial intelligence
so here John says free energy
minimization is a machine logic in its
own right empowering living as well as
artifactual organisms to optimally
resist entropy
um
and like this is I think
um like a shout out to like the many
uh people who are working on
using active inference in machine
learning instead of reinforcement
learning so
it's kind of great
and like he really talks about
um
like the ethics of that like what
happens when we like
um
you know have like he talks about the
singularity right like when machines
become like smarter than us
and he says
um that effectively the challenge is
moving from coding like programming with
even with active inference right so
coding to ethics like how are we going
to ethically like program the machines
so that um you know they're not like
self-driving cars aren't running over
you know people or or whatever right
like so there's the ethics and then to
um survival like like to human survival
right like like why like
um yeah if the machines get to equip
whatever they don't need us anymore like
why should they follow the ethics that
we've programmed into them I guess
Daniel
yeah this was a very interesting section
first we could imagine a kind of trolley
car problem with some organization and
some people and eventually the kind of
decidability that's going to have to
come into play there and the other
provocative aspect in this from coding
to ethics to survival is we often hear
you can't get an ought from an is so no
amount of mechanic definition is going
to result in an ethical imperative can't
get an Offerman is and that kind of
describes this Coatings to ethics
um difficulty you can't really get an
ethic just from how something is encoded
but
in a way survival is being proposed as a
post-ethical imperative
a first principles
we couldn't necessarily go from is to
ought
but we can go from is through ought back
to is which is survival
and so it kind of reincinuates
a type of
first principle ethic more like a work
ethic
than like a
moral ethic
but that opens up a lot of questions
about what kinds of Ethics are
of what status is
under or after the survival imperative
yeah it's interesting because like
I think with active inferences or free
energy governance specifically like
there are two ways where I think it's
interesting
one level is like thinking about an
organization as an organism was like
independent of my Human Experience of
that organism of like what makes organ
like this organism survive
and then I think the reason why I care
about it the most which is like my own
Human Experience of like how meaning is
created for me in an organization
and I think ultimately like that's
personally at least what I care about
the most and then when I think about AI
I'm like okay well like even if you have
an embedded a on your system if it
doesn't mean something personally to
humans in that organization like I don't
really care even if it makes
the organization survive more like it
more likely to survive
um so it's just like interesting these
two different takes of like
okay even if it makes the organization
more likely to survive like why do I
care if that doesn't isn't meaningful to
me as a human in that organization not
sure if that makes sense
um yeah so then
um also says first order principles such
as ai's free energy immunization will
lay the foundation for governance models
to increasingly self-organize
um so I think that like the the like
this is very meta it's like the um how
Daniel is saying like we go from coding
to ethics to survival I think like maybe
ethics is like the fog between like
coding and survival
um where like free energy minimization
um like is about persistence
um and like can be used in coding and
like will lay the foundation for
governance models to increasingly
self-organize so like self-organization
based on free energy minimization I
guess
yeah the section was interesting and I I
do think that there's uh like John is
super excited about Ai and uh
like we got a long way to go I mean
we'll get there it's not impossible it's
just gonna take some time I think I
don't know
any other thoughts here in artificial
intelligence
I mean I have lots of other thoughts
here but I think like getting to Sean's
perspective will be really fun
yeah I guess I'm just not I think the
thing I really am not quite
understanding here is the explainability
piece and I think I was trying to
mention this earlier of like if you have
an AI That's like bubbling up insights
about your organization saying like hey
this is what's going on or like this is
the right answer of what you should do
in this situation but it isn't like
understood by the people in that
organization like does it even matter
and is that what Bajan means by
explainability right like even if AI
gives you the right answer but it isn't
like
understood and integrated into the
people not organization
is that AI actually useful in our
organization
um and that's like the tension I've been
grappling with here and I don't quite
understand and he talks about a lot
about explainability of
predictions I'm not sure if that's
exactly what he's talking about or not
but good question for John
for sure
um and then the last section for um
future development is the board
capabilities developmental paths so he
says indeed the board is ultimately
responsible for anticipating the firm's
future capability constellation
including that of the board itself to
sustainably succeed with continuous
strategic renewal however to avoid the
cognitive traps related to individual
board profiles that Layman and Wallin
identified we must study the cognitive
micro foundations of capability
development at the board level
to date this area represents a void in
both strategy and governance research
like so I thought that this was cool
especially like with respect to
um
the active inference Institute like as
we are fleshing out our own board and
like what like the board decides what
this and future boards will be capable
of doing like now and forever
um it ends like they can always all this
stuff can be changed with approval of
the board right so
I think that um
I I liked this like capability
constellation
um phrase I thought that that was kind
of neat because there's a lot of like
there's a lot of little like
um
like sub capabilities right within the
board like there's committees and this
and that and like everybody can do or
take care of many different things or
like what don't we want the board to do
like it's the possibilities are pretty
like endless and
um expansive
but the
like what is purposeful and what is um
what will gain like the most bang for
the buck in terms of what should the
board focus on
that's kind of I don't know crazy
so um and then he outlined a little bit
of these cognitive traps um but I I
didn't go too far into them from here so
do you guys have anything here on board
capabilities
um oh
so
this so I did go actually a little bit
into them so what capabilities are
required at the level of the individual
board member when the necessary firm
capabilities are not yet developed and
so as Bhajan is thinking about this he
um goes to this Theory you which I had
never heard of before and so he outlines
three of the principles developed in
this Theory you and it looks like that
there's quite a few
um but he um talked about like what what
are the capabilities required at the
board member level when
um when we're defining the firm
capabilities like the board capabilities
for now and forever and so these I
really liked
um so he says number nine practice
principle number five is what it is
practice deep listening and dialogue
connect with your mind and heart wide
open when connecting to other people and
contacts open up all four channels of
listening listen from what you know from
what surprises you from the whole and
from what you sense once to emerge the
emerging whole and I really like this
like four different ways of listening
like it's something that we don't always
think about we just listen right and we
listen like in one way like we're just
like I listened to I heard this but when
you're like looking at listening
in different aspects it's it's different
right like listening from
listening from what surprises you like
from
um you know can you listen to it four
times and like pretend like you don't
know anything pretend like how does this
relate to what you already know I don't
know I thought that this was really nice
I don't know if you guys have like if
you were excited about it as as I was as
excited um or I couldn't read a
collective sense making next
or maybe Tyler wants to read to
Collective sense making
yeah sure and I was just gonna say I
really love the convergence of like new
Ag and corporate governance uh
literature kind of converging in real
energy governance it's wonderful
um all right so number 10 Collective
sense making so use social presencing
theater and embodied knowing so whatever
process you use to make sense of The
Learning Journey what matters most is
that you pay discipline attention to all
the voices and manifestations of the
field uh paying discipline attention
means that you are intentionally holding
back all inclinations to mix your own
interpretations or Solutions just spend
all that because you wanted the data of
the field to speak for you the data this
field cannot the field cannot speak to
you if your mind is too busy
okay
so that was also cool and then um
oh yeah but the data of the field cannot
speak to you if your mind is too busy
expressing opinions and proposing
Solutions oh that cuts to the core
um yeah sorry I guess I put that off and
then whatever my slide making
capabilities were
for subparts
um and then the last one the last
principle is principle 22. I'm like no
I'm like I want to read this Theory you
like what is this all about I'm like
totally interested in learning more
about these principles
um number 22 is create enabling
infrastructures that allow the system to
sense and see itself
um and he quotes making a system of
sentency itself can change the
coordination Dynamics among the players
in a field moving them toward ecosystem
awareness as traditional governance
models are increasingly uprooted in a
discontinuous world there is not only a
need for a new governance logic but
correspondingly new board capabilities
developmental paths specifically Duality
management as a dynamic board capability
demands dedicated research
um and that Duality management just to
like remind everyone is like financial
and strategic control so it's like both
of those things not one or the other
like they they both work together okay
huh
and then we can go into chapter 13 or if
you guys have more thoughts about this
is Theory you principles
no
um we can go into this uh
chapter 13 Tyler do you want to read
this um portion of the abstract for us
this classical cause effect determinism
upon which Paradigm of strategy
management uh as well as governance
research has been built is uprooted
paparian academics Relentless pursuit of
empirically establishing qualifying and
then falsifying mechanistic cause and
effect relationships is struggling to
inspire the business Community which is
itself we're doing too often with these
self-inflicted limitations of its own of
its very World models together Academia
practice or challenge to reconnect
organizing to that self-evancing
dimension of the universe's uh
information system fpg is as valid for
business organizations as it is for
political constructs or for that matter
matter navigating geopolitical
dislocations and death cycle disruptions
read this last
s from one top down bottom-up
hierarchical disconnectivity and a
top-down dominance of supervised content
prescriptions to an urge to adapt to the
outer World emitted incapacity for an
active inference and three the
non-existence of both a Timeless deep
purpose as well as meta capabilities is
naturally entropy-bound
in the absence of a generative Bayesian
model we become incapacitated indeed
camping on seesaws is the categorical
imperative of survival pursuing
self-organization organization as a
means not an end it is right here where
the fundamental difference between
traditional corporate governance and
free energy governance models lie free
energy governance sees through formal
organization as organizing manifests
itself as a self-organizing generative
model operating as a whole within and
without the firm embracing
self-organization as a self-evancing
universal information system
um and so he makes like I just pulled
out several claims that he made in this
chapter and a couple like little summary
uh sections because this is like the
official summary
um
he says together Academia and practice
are challenged to reconnect organizing
to that self-organizing or
self-evidencing Dimension inherit
inherent of the University's information
system to purposefully create extend or
modify the firm's resource base and
that's a quote from Health at Al and he
says to thrive and survive
purposeful behavior is one of life's
defining features but it is only
possible if living systems operate as a
whole it is only by managing information
that the cell can impose order on the
extreme complexity of its operations and
therefore fulfill its ultimate purpose
of staying alive and reproducing and
this is equipped from nurse 2020 and
like I just I don't know this is so hard
because
um and like I'll always go back to like
Mike Levin's beautiful explanation of
like
the constraints imposed by the larger
system on a smaller system because
a cell's ultimate purpose is not sting
Library producing in fact like if it's
one cell sure like but in a
multicellular organism some cells like
the purpose of the cell is to die like I
mean we all start off with like webbing
between the fingers and that webbing is
cells and then that webbing you know
goes away like so that cell in like the
construction of our existence and our
morphology like its purpose is to die so
um I guess that that's well like we were
talking about M A earlier like the
purpose of the smaller firm that gets
subsumed by a larger firm is also to
like die or become incorporated or to
somehow integrate with the current
larger firm and so these these
constraints
um
I I don't know so like the the nested
hierarchical levels like each top level
or each larger level constrains the
function of the inner level and also
that information
um so anyway sorry I have to just like
say that because it's otherwise it's not
um staying alive and reproducing is not
the purpose of cells sorry
I don't know if you guys said that too
um Bijan says
free energy as an information theoretic
rather than thermodynamic measure is
uniquely positioned to measure and guide
a firm's survivability as a
self-organizing information as well as
belief system
um and he quotes this book from Lindsay
2021 Daniel have you read this I haven't
read it but um it's like a Christian
Memoir I guess uh he says Kristen
recalls a thought he had as a teenager
there must be a way of understanding
everything by starting from nothing if
I'm only allowed to start off with one
point in the entire universe can I
derive everything else I need from that
in firsten's world the free energy
principle is now the nearly nothing that
can explain almost to everything
um I like this quote from this book and
it's like also like I've got to go read
it now like I don't know if it's is it a
Christian Memoir maybe it's just an
interview or like a long article or
something like that but I haven't read
it but it's like um someone else like
you know giving like a detail of
Kristen's like life and
ideas I guess
I don't know if you guys have thoughts
here
no yes no
okay
um
so and so I just want to just call out
uh
we talked we just talked about like very
early on like maybe it was like the
fourth video we did talk about like if
you're going what are we talking about
like thermodynamic versus
um information theoretic free energy
like go back because we we really did
get into that so if you're going what
are they talking about we did talk about
that quite a bit in one of the early
um videos so now might be a good time to
just like refresh your memory that we
did detail that so if that's looking
weird to you
um Go Go Get It Go Get a refresher okay
uh and then claim here in summary
will dissonance as an error minimizing
source for optimizing the accurate
accuracy of posterior beliefs rather
than explaining dissonance away is
essential to firm survival and
discontinuous environments
um and I liked this like informational
dissonance part this was like a couple
videos ago not that not that far in the
past but
um yeah
yeah so this like brought up the initial
communication question like does
everybody need to know everything all of
the time or
um and also like your information
getting updated with like the outside
information to like resolve the
dissonance
anyway there's that do you get some
thoughts here
all right I'm gonna make somebody else
read these because I'm tired of talking
tired of hearing myself talk uh Tyler do
you want to do this this is the building
blocks of an active inference so this is
a nice little summary uh recap of um
what we've learned so far all right
building blocks have been active
inference so one is the four states
that's active action sensory perception
internal firm resources and external the
hidden unknowns two one internal
external markovian boundary the site
where actions upon hidden States
generate outcomes a feed in circular
causality our perception and allow the
Precision enhancing updating of power
beliefs predictions
three one first order principle free
energy minimization that's a measure of
minimizing equivocally error and
uncertainty I.E the differences between
predictions prior beliefs and outcomes
posterior beliefs eventually everything
becomes miserable
thank you
um yeah and so Bichon makes this claim
that once managers start approaching
exploration in the form of an active
inference linking in circular causality
all four states conditioned by the Marco
blanket and governance by free energy
minimization we can straight away see
that success and exploration is
critically determined by the level of
sophistication of a few things first
prediction models a self-evidencing Eco
Niche model that connects corporate
Purpose with the very predictions The
Firm stipulates second the bounded set
of external states that the firm decides
to act upon to bottom-up sample the
world and test hypotheses with the least
required computational resource
investment and third belief updating
resulting from the consequences
posterior beliefs that the firm's
actions generate
and so this is also like a nice little
summary
section I thought
um and this can he continues to say it
is now self-evident to appreciate that
action is Central to perception more
importantly the firm's generative model
and actions controlled
ambiguity and uncertainty the firm's
generative model is the first Eco Niche
firm is more in control than it
traditionally resists to believe
the perception of uncertainty is after
Observer I.E firm specific
um and and I did like like that uh
like real uncertainty versus the
perception of uncertainty and when we're
talking about like embodied enacted
extended cognition it's all about like
your perception of uncertainty versus
actual uncertainty
so like you know unless you can count
cards you're uncertain of like if you're
playing Blackjack you don't you don't
know what your chances are of getting
21. but like if you can count cards
right like just that's just one example
like you're less uncertain if it's a
single deck Blackjack like you're less
uncertain as to what are the
possibilities as the game continues to
unfold
it's also interesting there with the um
kind of
Declaration of Independence like
self-evident appreciation
that reflects the real bright line
between passive inference and active
inference
and it's like that claim does one agree
or disagree and then if they did agree
then they have already seen their own
eye movement and decision to seek out
this information as Central to their
perception of that expression so it kind
of serves as like a co-on of
self-evidencing
and then there are some Downstream
applications for example
one that he attacks many times
throughout is that the external world is
not uncertain there's not uncertainty in
the Commodities Market there's an
observer dependent
uncertainty about external States
and about action selection and active
inference is it just is a generic family
of strategies for jointly resolving
uncertainty about external States and
actions that bring alignment AKA provide
pragmatic value so many of those
implications of FEG are Downstream of
the acceptance or acknowledgment that
action is Central to perception
very nice thank
you
um okay so he lists these requirements
for out performance and survival Tyler
do you want to read these for me yes
all right one at a Timeless uh deep
purpose to generative top-down bottom up
prediction error minimization form of
free energy minimizing inactive
inference three principled values and
aspirations determining Eco Niche
prosperity and sustainability if all
three elements are articulated and
simple explainable language and
communicated to all members within and
Beyond the firm's boundaries then the
firm's long-term process will be
sustainably enhanced in form of
self-organizing generative model the
board of directors rather than executive
leadership only must ensure that those
elements come to life and more
importantly stay alive
thanks
um and so sorry so this goes back to um
like we were talking about purpose
earlier like where does purpose come
from who decides what the purpose is uh
so this it was more talked about I think
a lot in this chapter
um and and we've also talked about it
before through the book so this is a
nice little wrap-up section
um and then goes on to make the claim
that free organization free organization
okay I've said organizations so many
times I think like if I were to count
like I probably have said the word
organization like a thousand times in
this live stream Maybe not maybe 150.
free energy governance is as valid for
business organizations as it is for
political constructs or for that matter
navigating geopolitical dislocations and
debt cycle disruptions any organism that
suffers from a one top-down bottom-up
disconnectivity two top-down dominance
of ideological and supervised content
prescriptions three dominant logic to
adapt to the outer World emitted
self-inflicted incapacity for an active
inference and not least four not an
existence of a times purpose as well as
Medicaid abilities such as listening to
what wants to emerge in the web of
random interactions and observing The
Observer is naturally entropy-bound and
incapacitated to navigate macro
disruptions
um so he gives that like recipe
for survival and outperformance
um here so and in the last requirements
for our performance and survival so I
think that those are just like the three
those are just like the inverse
statements of each other like this is
what we need this is what we can't have
um so that's a nice like way to wrap up
like how free energy governance will
contribute to
um the firm's outperformance and
survival in
the world competing with other firms and
such
um do you guys have any thoughts here
good
um okay and then I just pulled this
final quote out and we kind of alluded
to this earlier it says it does the
uncertainty that human humans face come
from the inherent instability of the
human landscape or from the perceptions
and belief systems that we have about
the human environment and this is kind
of nice
um
like what what is it that's unstable
like where is the uncertainty is the
uncertainty like in our perception or is
it in the world somewhere
so
um I don't know this is a nice like
thing to think about and
um in resolving that uncertainty through
action I think like gets to kind of the
core of free energy governance
um
here at the end of the book so
um thanks for listening I don't know if
you guys have any final thoughts on any
of the content presented here in these
two chapters or on the book overall or
you know questions that are growing
through your mind
nothing like that all right we're quick
through the concluding sections and um
we look forward to having an open
discussion with the author uh in a few
weeks as well as other participants who
have been keeping up with the content
so thanks guys
thank you Tyler thank you blue
farewell